现在我们知道了如何构建分组密码
Now that we know that block cyphers are we
know how to construct them, let's see how
我们看在安全加密中如何使用它们
但在此之前，我想简单提醒大家
to use them for secure encryption? But
before that, I wanna briefly remind you of
一个重要的抽象概念叫做伪随机函数
an important abstraction called a
pseudo-random function, and a
还有伪随机置换。那么如上一章所讲
pseudo-random permutation. So as we said
in the last module, a block cipher's map,
分组密码将N位输入映射到N位输出
我们看了两个分组密码的例子
N bits of inputs to N bits of outputs. And
we saw two examples of block ciphers,
3DES和AES。现在，一个重要的
关于分组密码的抽象概念是
triple DES and AES. Now, an important
abstraction of the concept of a block
PRP和PRF蕴涵的想法。记住
cipher, is captured by this idea of a PRP
and a PRF. And remember that a
一个伪随机函数PRF，是一个两个输入的函数
pseudo-random function, a PRF, basically
is a function that takes two inputs. It
取一个密钥和某个集合X里的元素作为输入
输出某个集合Y里的元素
takes a key and an element in some set X.
And in outputs an element in some set Y
现在唯一的要求是存在一个有效的算法
and for now the only requirement is that
there's an efficient algorithm to evaluate
来计算这个函数。我们待会来讨论PRF的安全性
this function. We're going to talk about
security for PRFs in just a minute. And
类似地，有一个相关概念叫做伪随机置换
then similarly, there's a related concept
called a pseudo-random permutation, which
和PRF类似。事实上，也有一个有效算法
可以用来计算伪随机置换
is similar to a PRF. In fact, there's also
an efficient algorithm to evaluate, the
但是，伪随机置换多了一个要求
pseudo-random permutation. However,
there's an additional requirement, that
那就是存在一个算法D可以计算函数E的逆
there's also an algorithm D that will
invert this function E. So a PRP, is
所以一个PRP也是PRF，但函数必须是
对所有密钥一一映射的
basically a PRF, but where the function is
required to be one to one for all keys.
还得有一个有效的求逆的算法。
现在我们讨论
And there is an efficient inversion
algorithm. So now let's talk about how to
如何定义安全的PRF。我们已经说过，PRF的目标是
define secure PRFs. So we already said
that essentially the goal of a PRF is to
看上去要像一个从集合X到Y的随机函数
为了更精确地理解这一点
look like a random function from the set X
to Y. So to capture that more precisely we
我们定义这个记号，Funs(X,Y)表示所有
从集合X映射到集合Y的函数
define this notation, Funs XY to be the
set of all functions from the set X, to
类似地，我们定义集合S_F为所有从集合X到Y的
the set Y. Similarly, we defined the set S
sub F to be the set of all functions from
由PRF定义的函数。换句话说，一旦固定了密钥K
the set X to Y that are defined by the
PRF. In other words. Once you fix the key
就获得了一个从集合X到集合Y的函数
K, you obtain a function from the set X to
the set Y. And the set of all such
所有这些集合的函数组成的集合，给定PRF，
也就是S_F。那么我们上次说过
functions, given a particular PRF, would
be the set S sub F. So as we said last
Funs(X,Y)是一个庞大的集合，所有从集合S到Y的函数
time, Funs XY is generally a gigantic set
of all functions from S to Y. I think I
我想我提到过，事实上，对于AES，X和Y大小
都是2的128次方
mentioned that, in fact, for AES, where X
and Y are two to the 128, the size of the
这个函数集合的大小就是
2的128次方的2的128次方次方
set is two to the 128 times two to the
128. It's a double exponential, which is
是个极为巨大的数。另一方面
an absolutely enormous number. On the
other hand, the number of functions
AES分组密码定义的函数数目为2的128次方个
defined by the AES block cipher is just
two to the hundred and twenty-eight.
一个函数对应一个密钥。我们说
Namely, one function from each key. And
what we would like to say is that a random
从这个大集合中随机选择，与
choice from this huge set is
indistinguishable from a random choice
从这个小集合里随机选择无法区分。
这里无法区分的意思
from the small set. And what do we mean by
indistinguishable, we mean that an
一个攻击者可以和这里的一个随机函数交互
adversary who can interact with a random
function in here, can't distinguish that
他将无法区分他到底是否在和一个随机函数互动
interaction from an interaction with a
random function in here. Now let's find
更清楚点，我们通常定义两个实验
out more precisely. So we're gonna, as
usual, define two experiments. Experiment
实验0和实验1。我们的目标是
zero and experiment one. And our goal is
to say that the adversary can't
攻击者无法区分这两个实验，在实验0里
distinguish these two experiments. So in
experiment zero, the challenger,
挑战者选择一个伪随机函数
basically, is gonna choose a random,
pseudo-random function. Okay? So he's
他随机选定一个密钥K，K确定了这个函数f
gonna fix the key K at random, and that's
gonna define this function, little f over
f是PRF实现的函数之一
here, to be one of the functions
implemented by the PRF. And experiment
在实验1里，挑战者选择一个真随机函数
one, on the other hand, the challenger is
gonna choose a truly random function from
从集合X映射到集合Y的。我们称这一真随机函数
the set X to the set Y. And again, we're
gonna call this truly random function
为f。不管是哪一个实验
little f, either way, either experiment
zero or experiment one, the challenger
挑战者总是选出函数f，不是从PRF中
ends up with this little function f that's
either chosen from the PRF, or chosen as a
就是从X到Y的全体函数中。现在攻击者
询问这个函数f
truly random function from X to Y. Now the
adversary basically gets to query this
他提交一份询问X1，获得了f在X1的值
function, little f. So he gets to submit a
query X1 and he obtains the value of f at
然后他又提交了一份X2的询问，获得f在X2的值
the point X1, then he gets to submit at
X2, and he obtains the value of f at the
等等。攻击者询问了Q次
point X2. So on and so fourth, he makes Q
queries. And so he learns the value of the
他学到了f在这Q个点的值
现在他的目标是确定
function little f at those Q points. Now
his goal is to say whether the function
函数f是否是从Funs(X,Y)里随机选择的
little f is chosen truly at random from
Funs XY, or chosen just from the set of
或者是从PRF实现的函数集里。
所以攻击者输出一位b'作为判断
functions implemented by the PRF. So he
outputs a certain bit b prime and we'll
我们把这个输出作为实验的输出
实验0或实验1的
refer to that output as the output of
experiments, either as experiment zero or
通常我们说PRF是安全的
experiment one. As usual we say that the
PRF is secure. If, in fact, the adversary
如果攻击者无法区分这两个实验
换句话说，他对实验0输出1的概率
can't distinguish these two experiments.
In other words, the probability that he
跟对实验1输出1的概率几乎一样
outputs one, experiments zero is the same,
pretty much the same as the probability
换句话说，这两个概率的差别是可以忽略的
that he outputs one in experiment one. In
other words, the difference of these two
这个抓住了一个事实
probabilities is negligible. So this
captures nicely, the fact that the
攻击者无法区分一个伪随机函数和
adversary couldn't distinguish a
pseudo-random function from a truly random
一个真随机函数，从X到Y的。现在
安全伪随机置换的定义
function from the set X to Y. Now, the
definition for a secure pseudo-random
安全PRP，是一个安全的分组密码
permutation, a secure PRP, which is
basically a secure block cipher, is pretty
非常相似。在实验0中，攻击者选择了
much the same. In experiment zero, the
adversary's gonna choose a random instance
PRP的一个随机样本。那么他选择一个随机的K
定义函数f为伪随机置换中
of the PRP. So he's gonna choose a random
K, and define little f to be the function
对应k的函数
that corresponds to little k within the
pseudo-random permutation. In experiment
实验1中，攻击者不随机选择一个X到Y的函数
one, the adversary is gonna choose not a
truly random function from X to Y, but a
而是随机选择一个X到X的函数，对吧？
那么PRP的目标是
truly random one to one function from X to
X. Okay? So the goal of our PRP is to look
和X到X的随机置换长得像，
即一个随机的一一映射函数
like a random permutation from X to X.
Namely, a random one to one function from
从集合X到它自身的。那么这里的函数f
the set X to itself. So the little
functional little f here is again gonna be
也是个随机函数，从集合X到它自身。
a random function. From the set X to
itself. And again, the challenger ends up
(其实这时的f应该是PRP)
挑战者选定了这个函数f。前面说过，
攻击者提交了询问
with this function, little f. As before,
the adversary gets to submit queries and
它获得了这些询问的结果
it gets to see the results of those
queries. And then he shouldn't be able to
攻击者不应该能区分实验0和实验1
distinguish, again, experiment zero from
experiment one. So again, given the value
给定函数f在Q个攻击者选取的点的值
of the function f at Q points chosen by
the adversary, he can't tell whether the
攻击者无法断定函数f是伪随机置换PRP
或是X到X的真随机置换
function f came from a PRP, or
whether it's a truly random permutation
那么我们看一个简单例子：
假设集合X只包含两个点
from X to X. So let's look at a simple
example. Suppose the set X contains only
0和1.这时，Perms[X]是容易定义的
two points, zero and one. In this case,
Perms[X] is really easy to define.
有两个点，我们看，0，1
Essentially, there are two points, and
we're looking at, you know, 01. And we're
我们问，所有这个集合上的可逆函数的集合是什么？
asking, what is the set of all invertible
functions on the set 01? Well, there are
只有两个这样的函数。一个是恒等函数
only two such functions. One function is
the identity function. And the other
另一个是交叉映射的函数，就是这个
function is basically the function that
does crossovers, namely this function
集合｛0,1｝上只有两个可逆函数
here. These are the only two invertible
functions in the set 01. So really, Perms[X]
所以Perms[X]只包含两个函数
现在我们看下面这个PRP
only contains two functions, in this
case. Now, let's look at the following
密钥空间是｛0,1｝，当然X是｛0,1｝
PRP. The key space is gonna be 01, and of
course, X is gonna be 01. And let's define
我们定义PRP为X异或K。这是我们的PRP。
我给大家的问题是
the PRP as basically X XOR K. Okay so
that's our PRP and my question to you is,
这个PRP安全吗？换句话说，这个PRP
是否和Perms[X]上的随机函数不可区分？
is this a secure PRP? In other words, is
this PRP indistinguishable from a random
我希望大家的答案是肯定的
function on Perms[X]? I hope everybody
said, yes, because essentially, the sets
本质上，这个PRP实现的函数
和Perms[X]里的函数是一模一样的
of functions implemented in this PRP, is
identical to the set of functions in Perms[X].
所以随机选择的密钥和随机选择的函数是一样的
So a random choice of key here is
identical to a random choice of function
因此，这两个分布，伪随机或真随机
over here. And as a result, the two
distributions, either pseudo-random or
它们是相等的。很清楚，攻击者不能区分
random, are identical. So clearly, an
adversary can't distinguish the two
这两个分布。现在，我们说过，
我们有一些安全PRP的例子
distributions. Now, we already said that
we have a couple of examples of secure
3DES和AES。我只想提一下
PRPs triple DES and AES. And I just wanted
to mention that, if you want to make
如果想更具体些，这里有一个关于AES的具体假设
things very concrete, here's a concrete
security assumptions about AES. Just to
给个例子，所有算法运行时间需要2^80的
give an example, say that all algorithms
had run in time 2^80 have advantage
对AES都有优势，最多为2^-40
这是一个关于AES的合理假设
against AES of at most 2^-40. This
is, a reasonable assumption about AES, and
我只想说的更具体些
I just wanted to state it for
concreteness. So let's look at another
我们看另外一个例子。考虑上个问题里的PRP
example. Consider again the PRP from the
previous question. Namely XX or K.
记住集合X只含一位，0或1
Remember the set X was just one bit,
namely the value zero and one. And this
这次我们问，这个PRP是不是个安全的PRF？
time, we're asking, is this PRP a secure
PRF? In other words, is this PRP
换句话说，这个PRP是不是与一个X到X的随机函数不可区分呢？
indistinguishable from a random function
from X to X? Now, the set of random
X到X的随机函数的集合Funs[X,X]
这里只含四个元素
functions from X to X, Funs[X,X] in
this case, contains only four elements.
有两个可逆函数，刚才我们看过了
There are the two invertible functions,
which we already saw in... I believe the
恒等函数和相反函数
identity function, and the negation
function, the function that
相反函数将0射到1，1射到0
不过还有两个函数
sends zero to one, and one to zero. But
there are two other functions. Namely, the
一个函数将一切都射为0
另一个将一切都射为1
function that sends everything to zero.
And the function that sends everything to
好，这四个函数都在Funs[X,X]里。问题是
one. Okay, these are four functions inside
Funs[X,X], and the question is: Is this
我们刚才看的这个PRP，与从Funs[X,X]中的
PRP that we just looked at, is it also
indistinguishable from a random choice
随机选择是否不可区分？我希望大家都说不是。
不是安全PRF的原因是
from Funs[X,X]? So I hope everybody said no
and the reason it's not a secure PRF is
有一个简单的攻击，攻击者用来区分
because there's a simple attack, namely
the attacker supposed to distinguish
他是否在和这个PRF交互，还是和一个
whether he's interacting with this PRP or
is he interacting with a random function
Funs[X,X]里的随机函数交互
区分方法很简单
from Funs[X,X]. And the distinguisher
is very simple. Basically we're gonna
我们询问函数在x=0和x=1处的值
query the function at both x equals zero
and x equals one, and then if we get a
如果我们获得了一个碰撞，换句话说，如果
f(0)=f(1)，那么我们一定不是在和PRP交互
collision, in other words, if f of zero is
equal to f of one, then for sure we're not
也就是不能输出1了。换句话说
interacting with a PRP. In which case we
can just output one. In other words we're
我们在和一个随机函数交互。换句话说，输出0
interacting with a random function. In
other words we say zero. So let's look at
我们来看这个区分方法的优势。
当它和一个PRP交互时
the advantage of this distinguisher. Well
when it's interacting with a PRP, it'll
它从不输出1，因为f(0)永远不可能等于f(1)的
never output a one, because f of zero can
never be equal to f of one. In other
换句话说，攻击者输出1的概率为0
但是，当我们和一个
words, the probability of outputting one
is zero. However, when we interact with a
Funs[X,X]中的真随机函数交互时
f(0)=f(1)的概率就是严格的1/2
truly random function in Funs[X,X],
the probability that f of zero is equal to
因为有一半的函数满足f(0)=f(1)
f of one is exactly one-half.  Cause half the
functions satisfy F of zero's equal to F
另一半的函数则不。所以我们输出1的概率是1/2
of one, and half the functions don't. So
then, we'll output one with probability
那么这个区分方法的优势是1/2，是不可忽略的
one-half. So the advantage of this
distinguisher is one-half, which is non-negligible.
因此，这个PRP不是安全的PRF
And as a result, this PRP here
is not a secure PRF. Now it turns out this
实际上这里X太小了，使得这个PRP不是PRF
事实上有一个重要的引理
only true because if set X is very small.
And in fact there is an important lemma,
叫做PRF转换引理，告诉我们一个安全的PRP
事实上也是安全的PRF
called the PRF Switching Lemma, that
says that a secure PRP, is in fact a
只要集合X足够大
secure PRF, whenever the set X is
sufficiently large. And by sufficiently
足够大的意思是，比如AES的输出空间是2的128次方
large, I mean say the output space of AES
which is two to the 128th. So by this
根据这个引理，我们待会还要细说之
如果AES是一个安全的PRP
lemma which will state more precisely in a
second, AES if it's a secure PRP, it is
它还是一个安全的PRF。那么这个引理阐述了下面的事实
also a secure PRF. So this lemma basically
says the following, if you give me a PRP
如果给我一个集合X上的PRP，那么对于任何攻击者
询问PRP最多Q个点
over the set X, then for any adversary that
queries the PRP, at at most Q points, so it
问挑战的函数最多Q个点的值
makes at most Q queries into the
challenge function. Then, the difference
然后，他攻击PRP时对比真随机函数的优势
between its advantage in attacking the PRP
when compared to a random function, is
和区分PRP与随机置换的优势相差很小
very close to its advantage in
distinguishing the PRP from a random
事实上，这个差别被这个量所限制
permutation. In fact the difference, is
bounded by this quantity here, and since
(提示：第一章里的生日攻击)
由于我们说|X|非常大，这个Q平方除以2|X|
将是可以忽略的
we said that X is very large, this
quantity Q squared over 2X is negligible.
好，这是我们的目标。本质上，当X很大
Okay. That's gonna be our goal. So
essentially, again, when X is large, say
比如2的128次方，Q比如是2的32次方
即攻击者做出了十亿次的询问
two to the 128, Q say is going to be two
to the 32. That's a billion queries that
然后，这个优势的上界依然是可以忽略的
the adversary makes. Then, still the ratio
is going to be negligible. In which case,
我们说这个攻击者的优势是区分PRP
we say that the adversary's advantage is
distinguishing the PRP from a random
和一个随机函数的。两者几乎一样
区分PRP和随机置换的优势可以忽略
function. It's pretty much the same as its
advantage of distinguishing a PRP from a
因此，如果E已是个安全的PRP
random permutation. So, again, it's
basically, if E is already a secure PRP,
那么它也是个安全的PRF。那么对于AES
我们相信，AES是一个安全的PRP
then it's already a secure PRF. So for
AES, AES, we believe, is a secure PRP.
因此我们还可以把AES当作一个安全的PRF
And therefore, AES, we can also use it as a
secure PRF. And so, as a final note, I
最后我想提一下，从今往后，大家可以忘掉
just want to mention that, really, from
now on, you can kinda forget about the
AES和3DES的内部工作原理了
我们简单假设它们俩都是安全的PRP
inner workings of AES and triple DES.
We're simply gonna assume that both are
然后我们看怎么使用它们。每当我说PRP
secure PRPs, and then we're gonna see how
to use them. But whenever I say PRP, or
或PRF，你应该想到AES或3DES，作为例子
PRF, you should be thinking in your mind,
basically, AES or triple DES.